[MUSIC]
So let's take a deeper look
at these lifecycle methods.
The first method that
gets called is OnCreate.
OnCreate gets called when
the activity is first created.
Typically OnCreate is used to
initialize the activity and
will carry out the following
four functions.
It will call super.onCreate so Android
can do some of its own initialization.
It will set the activity's content view,
which tells Android what the activity's
user interface should be.
Next, it will capture and
retain any references it needs to
the various views or
elements of the user interface.
And finally, it will configure the user
interface views and elements as required.
So, let's take a look at
MapLocation's onCreate method.
Here I've opened up the MapLocation
application in Eclipse.
And now,
I'll open up the MapLocation activity.
And here, as you can see, the MapLocation
class is a subclass of Activity and
it overrides Activity.onCreate.
Inside the onCreate method, you see
the four functions we just talked about.
First, there's a call to super.onCreate.
Next, there's a call to setContentView,
passing in the ID of a layout
file as a parameter.
After that, the activity stores
references to an EditText view and
to a button which appear
in the user interface.
And finally, onCreate attaches
a listener to the button.
Android calls this listener code every
time the user presses this button.
So, this listener code is listening,
for presses of the button.
OnRestart is another lifecycle method.
It gets called if the activity has been
stopped, but is about to be started again.
And you can use onRestart to handle any
special processing that you need, that, or
that is needed only after the activity's
been stopped, but is about to start again.
onStart is called when the activity
is about to become visible.
And some typical applications for
this method include starting when
visible-only behaviors, like
requesting location sensor updates, or
loading or
resetting persistent application state,
things like updating the unread messages
queue for an email reader application.
The onResume method gets called
when the activity is visible and
about to start interacting with the user.
And some things you do in this method
are to start foreground-only behaviors,
things like starting animations or
playing a background sound track.
onPause is called when your
activity is about to lose focus.
In this method,
you can shut down foreground-only
behaviors, things like killing animations.
And you should also save any persistent
state that the user has edited.
onStop is called when the activity
is no longer visible to the user.
At this point, it's possible that
the activity may be restarted later.
So, some typical things to do here
include caching activity state that
you'll want to restore when the activity
is later restarting and onStart is called.
And remember, onStop is not always
called when an activity terminates.
For instance, it may not be called
if Android kills the application's
process due to low memory.
So don't wait to save
persistent data in this method.
Go do that back in onPause.
onDestroy is called with the activity
is about to be destroyed and
some typical actions to do here
include releasing activity resources.
For example, shutting down private threads
that were started by this activity.
And again, remember,
onDestroy may not be called at all.
For example, when Android kills
an application due to low memory on
the device.
So, returning back to MapLocation,
you'll see that I've also overridden
most of the activity lifecycle methods,
including onStart,
onRestart, onResume, onPause,
onStop, and onDestroy.
In each of these methods, you'll see that
I placed a method call that logs some
information about the method being called.
And I encourage you to run
the MapLocation application yourself and
to watch the logcat view to see
exactly what's being written.
And I want you to try pressing different
buttons like the Back button and
the Home button, and
different keys to verify for yourself that
the lifecycle method calls are following
the graphic depiction that we saw earlier.
So now that we've seen
the activity lifecycle in action,
let's take a look at how one activity can
programatically start another activity.
To start an activity programatically,
you first create
an Intent object that specifies
the activity that you want to start.
And then you pass this newly
created Intent to methods such as
startActivity or startActivityForResult.
startActivity will start
up the desired activity,
pushing the current activity
out of the foreground.
startActivityForResult will also
start up the desired activity, but
it will do so with the expectation
that the started activity will
provide a result back to
that calling activity.
And in this case, the result is
communicated back by a call to
that activity's onActivityResult method.
And we'll come back to
that in a few minutes.
So, for now,
let's go back into Eclipse and
look at how MapLocation actually
starts up the Google Maps activity.
Here I'm showing where MapLocation
has attached a listener to
the Show Map button.
Whenever the user clicks this button, the
listener's onClick method will be called.
And as you can see,
that code creates an Intent and
then pass Intent to
the startActivity method.
And the end result of this is that
a Google Maps activity will open up,
showing a map centered on
the address that the user entered.
Now, you remember that entering an address
in MapLocation was pretty slow.
Well, here I'm going to show you
a different application that, instead of
asking the user to enter an address
through the keyboard, will allow him or
her to select a contact from the Contacts
application and allow him or
her to use the address of that contact
as the address to center the map on.
Let's take a look at this application
called MapLocationFromContacts.
So here's my device running.
I'll launch the MapLocationFromContacts
application.
And now you see a button that will
allow me to select an address from
an existing contact.
When I click on that button,
a new activity is started.
Now, this activity is actually part of
the Contacts application which will
show me my contacts and
allow me to select one of them.
So here, I'll do that and
I'll select my own name, Adam Porter.
Now, the Contacts application
has no idea what I
want to do with this selected contact.
In particular, it can't start or
show the map itself based on this contact.
It just wasn't designed to do that.
So what I've actually got happening
here is that MapLocationFromContacts has
asked the Contacts application
to return the data to it
once the user selects the contact.
And it does that by starting
the Contacts application via
a startActivityForResult,
rather than by using startActivity.
Now, once the contact is selected,
MapLocationsFromContacts will then
receive the selected data and it will call
Google Maps to display that information.
So let's see that in the code.
Now here, I'm opening
the MapLocationFromContacts application in
Eclipse.
And the structure of the main
activity is pretty similar to
what we saw in MapLocation, but
you'll notice that the code in the button
listener is a little bit different.
In particular, this code creates
a slightly different Intent and
then passes that Intent as a parameter
to startActivityForResult.
We'll look at intents in more
detail in the next lesson.
But you can also see here that
startActivityForResult takes
a second parameter,
which represents a request code.
And this will come in handy later
when the result is returned back to
the started activity.
Once the new activity is started,
it is responsible for
setting the result that should be
returned back to the calling activity.
And it does this by calling
Activity.setResult, passing in
a result code and
optionally passing in some result data.
Now, these result codes include some
built-in code such as RESULT_CANCELED,
which indicates that the user chose
not to complete the activity normally.
They probably hit the Back button,
for example.
And RESULT_OK, indicating that
the activity, in fact, completed normally.
Developers can also add
custom result codes after
the built-in result code,
RESULT_FIRST_USER.
Now, before the activity ends,
the activity must set its
result by calling setResult and
this result will eventually be
transmitted back to the calling activity
via the call to onActivityResult.
So let's take a look at that code in
the MapLocationFromContacts application.
Here's onActivityResult.
As you can see, its parameters include
the initial request code that was
passed into startActivityForResult,
the result
code used by the started activity
when it called setResult, and
an Intent object if it was passed
in when setResult was called.
onActivityResult usually starts off
by checking the result code and
request codes to determine what to
do with that particular result.
In this example, the next steps are to
retrieve the underlying contact data and
to parse it to extract just
the postal address of the contact.
Now, the details aren't important now,
so I'll skip over them.
But once the postal address
has been extracted,
MapLocationFromContacts operates
just like MapLocation did.
It processes the data so that it's in a
format that Google Map expects, puts that
data into an Intent object, and then call
startActivity, passing in that Intent.
The last topic I'll discuss today
is handling configuration changes.
A device's configuration
refers to device and
application characteristics related
to application resources, things like
languages used, screen size, keyboard
availability, and device orientation.
Now, these characteristics
can change at runtime.
And when they do, Android will
usually kill the current activity and
then restart it with the appropriate
resources for the changed configuration.
Now, since configuration changes
can happen frequently while using
an application, you want to make sure
that your lifecycle method code is fast.
Consider device orientation changes,
for example.
If you move the device from portrait
mode to landscape mode, and back to
portrait mode, that will cause the current
activity to be killed and restarted twice.
So if your startup code is slow,
that's really going to affect your
users' experience with your application.
So, to improve the speed of
configuration changes if you need it,
Android allows you to do two things.
One, as the change is occurring,
you can create and save
an arbitrary Java object that essentially
caches important state information.
And two, you can manually handle
the configuration change,
avoiding the whole shutdown and
restart sequence all together.
Let's talk about each one
of those one at a time.
So to speed up reconfiguration, I said
you can cached hard to recompute data and
store it in a Java object.
And one way to do this is by overriding
the onRetainNonConfigurationInstance
method, which will be called some
time between onStop and onDestroy.
And the object that you build and
return in onRetainNonConfigurationInstance
can be retrieved when
the activity is recreated by calling
getLastNonConfigurationInstance.
And that's usually done during the call to
the activity's onCreate method when you
recreate the activity.
Now, note that these methods
have been deprecated in favor of
other methods in the Fragment class.
And we haven't discussed fragments yet,
but
we'll come back to it in
a later lesson when we do.
Now, the second thing you can do to speed
up reconfiguration is to avoid the whole
kill and restart sequence altogether for
specific configuration changes.
And to do this, you declare
those specific changes that the,
your activity will handle in
the AndroidManifest.xml file.
For example, this XML snippet indicates
that MyActivity will manually
handle changes in device orientation and
screen size and keyboard accessibility.
So, if you do handle some
configuration changes manually,
then when those configuration
changes occur in runtime,
your activity will receive a call
to onConfigurationChanged.
And as a parameter, this method
will receive a Configuration object
which details the new configuration, so
your code can then read this object and
make whatever changes it needs to.